<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Simon Schreiber | Product Management Consultant</title>
    <link>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Simon Schreiber | Product Management Consultant</description>
    <image>
      <title>Simon Schreiber | Product Management Consultant</title>
      <url>https://www.sischreiber.com/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</url>
      <link>https://www.sischreiber.com/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.135.0</generator>
    <language>de-de</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Organizing for AI: Structures That Scale</title>
      <link>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/org/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/org/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The challenge with AI isn’t just the technology. Often it’s how organizations are structured around it. Whether the work involves building internal AI infrastructure or shipping &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/ai/&#34;&gt;user-facing AI features&lt;/a&gt;, the ability to ship depends on how teams are set up and work together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s where &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/tt/&#34;&gt;Team Topologies&lt;/a&gt; comes in because if the org chart is a mess, no amount of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/algorithms/&#34;&gt;machine learning&lt;/a&gt; will save it. The following four patterns outline how teams can be organized to support sustainable and effective use of AI.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Understanding Transformer Architecture Helps Craft Better LLM Prompts</title>
      <link>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/llm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/llm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is 2025 and AI is well beyond the experimental phase. It is now embedded in the daily workflows of product teams. Language models assist with drafting OKRs, identifying gaps in strategy, screening interview responses, analyzing churn data and generating test scenarios from acceptance criteria. Most of these tasks are powered by large language models (LLMs).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-happens-during-prompting&#34;&gt;What Happens During Prompting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you type a prompt into ChatGPT or Claude, the model replies with something fluent and useful. But what actually happens inside? An LLM is a deep neural network trained on vast amounts of text. It generates responses by predicting one token at a time. This entire process runs on the Transformer architecture, the foundation behind models like GPT-4, Claude and Gemini.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Team Topologies in a Nutshell</title>
      <link>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/tt/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/tt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With Team Topologies, Matthew Skelton and Manuel Pais aim to reduce the complexity of tech organizations to four team types and three modes of interaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The end goal is to help teams produce software that aligns with customer needs and is easier to build, run, and own. (Skelton &amp;amp; Pais)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;framework-influences&#34;&gt;Framework-Influences&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the central theses is that software architectures and the way teams interact are closely connected. This can be attributed to Conway’s Law, which states that an organization’s communication structures influence its software architecture.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to Split Cross-Functional Product Development Teams</title>
      <link>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/teams/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/teams/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What is the best way to split a cross-functional product development team? Here are six approaches with their respective pros and cons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-feature-teams&#34;&gt;1. Feature Teams&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A cross-functional team with the end-to-end ownership of a feature. For example, an e-commerce checkout process or product recos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The members of the feature team work directly on all code bases required to further develop the feature, even if they are not responsible for that part of the software system themselves.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Product Repo: A Curated Collection of Product Management Resources</title>
      <link>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/product-repo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/product-repo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Product Repo is my personal, curated collection of product management articles that I find worth reading. The list is organized into categories such as product-led growth, strategy, leadership, product management fundamentals and many more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find it here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sischreiber/product-repo/&#34;&gt;https://github.com/sischreiber/product-repo/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s essentially a GitHub readme file in my rather sparse repo, which I update sporadically whenever I come across noteworthy articles.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>[Mind the Product] The Irony of Product-Led Growth: How Adding More Can Slow You Down</title>
      <link>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/subtraction/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/subtraction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Glad to have my article on &lt;em&gt;Mind the Product&lt;/em&gt; where I attempt to explain why we have a bias toward increasing the scope of our products, even though evidence suggests that subtracting features can increase the overall value for users, customers and the business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mindtheproduct.com/the-irony-of-product-led-growth/&#34;&gt;https://www.mindtheproduct.com/the-irony-of-product-led-growth/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>6 Timeless Product Insights From Engineering Leaders</title>
      <link>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/pe/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/pe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Software engineers don’t go to product managers to understand how to build a software application. But when engineers start sharing their knowledge about product, there is often something in those words. Especially when the authors have left a footprint in the tech industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;joel-spolsky-on-the-worst-possible-strategic-mistake&#34;&gt;Joel Spolsky on the Worst Possible Strategic Mistake&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joel Spolsky is one of the co-founders of Stack Overflow. Although he has hardly posted on &amp;ldquo;Joel on Software&amp;rdquo; for years, there are several timeless articles worth reading. One of them is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.joelonsoftware.com/2000/04/06/things-you-should-never-do-part-i/&#34;&gt;“Things You Should Never Do, Part I”&lt;/a&gt; from 2000. It is about a specific strategic mistake in the tech industry and why the cause lies in the rule of thumb that code is harder to read than to write.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Saying No</title>
      <link>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/no/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/no/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Gatekeepers say &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; to everything. Proxies give a &lt;em&gt;yes&lt;/em&gt; to every idea. How do you find the right balance?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-problem-with-saying-_no_&#34;&gt;The Problem With Saying &lt;em&gt;No&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are hundreds of articles online about how and why product managers should say &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt;. In this context, negating refers to stakeholder requests that aim to change the scope of a product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the short term, product managers get some breathing room by rejecting requests. A frequently encountered quote comes from Warren Buffett: Saying &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; to almost everything is a characteristic of successful people. This may apply to many professions. But also if your focus is on user-driven products?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>[Mind the Product] The Advantages of Declarative Over Imperative User Stories</title>
      <link>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/declarative/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/declarative/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;How writing declaratively improves team collaboration and ultimately the product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mindtheproduct.com/the-advantages-of-declarative-user-stories/&#34;&gt;https://www.mindtheproduct.com/the-advantages-of-declarative-user-stories/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Headless CMS Pitfalls</title>
      <link>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/cms/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/cms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Headless CMS offer numerous advantages over traditional monolithic CMS, especially in a cloud-native stack. As is often the case, vendors&amp;rsquo; product marketing only mentions the advantages. After two headless CMS projects, I have summarized the pitfalls to watch out for on HackerNoon:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://hackernoon.com/what-they-dont-tell-you-about-headless-cms&#34;&gt;https://hackernoon.com/what-they-dont-tell-you-about-headless-cms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Much a Sprint Costs</title>
      <link>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/sprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/sprint/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sprints in Scrum need to be planned conscientiously. The personnel costs of an average sprint are easily in the five-digit range. Published on the Product Coalition, one of the largest product management communities:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://productcoalition.com/the-economics-of-sprint-planning-b20082d5e24e&#34;&gt;https://productcoalition.com/the-economics-of-sprint-planning-b20082d5e24e&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to Create a Portfolio Website: A Step-by-Step Process With Examples</title>
      <link>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/portfolio/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/portfolio/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;How I built my previous portfolio website with Hugo static site generator and hosted it on GitHub. The nice thing about this setup is that there are no costs other than the domain. My site looks different now but the setup is identical:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/the-kickstarter/how-to-create-a-product-portfolio-website-with-hugo-and-github-28daa950939c&#34;&gt;https://medium.com/the-kickstarter/how-to-create-a-product-portfolio-website-with-hugo-and-github-28daa950939c&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Product Backlog: Guidelines and Best Practices</title>
      <link>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/backlog/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/backlog/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The best practices I have acquired over time for setting up and managing a product backlog. Published on &amp;ldquo;Bootcamp&amp;rdquo;, a collection of resources about UX, UI and product management on medium.com:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/design-bootcamp/product-backlog-guidelines-and-best-practices-f52d1e12c1e5&#34;&gt;https://medium.com/design-bootcamp/product-backlog-guidelines-and-best-practices-f52d1e12c1e5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More Than Data: How to Understand and Measure AI Products</title>
      <link>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Written before the GenAI boom with a focus on quantifying AI product development. Published on Outvise, one of the leading marketplaces for business tech experts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.outvise.com/how-understand-and-measure-ai-products/&#34;&gt;https://blog.outvise.com/how-understand-and-measure-ai-products/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>8 Algorithms to Build Machine Learning Products</title>
      <link>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/algorithms/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/algorithms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For many, mathematical statistics was a dry subject matter at school and university. Without reference to reality. Well, then AI/machine learning products came along and linear regression suddenly became fun:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/swlh/8-algorithms-to-build-machine-learning-products-36695241682f&#34;&gt;https://medium.com/swlh/8-algorithms-to-build-machine-learning-products-36695241682f&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Beginners Guide to AI Product Management</title>
      <link>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/ai/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/ai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Written before the market entry of ChatGTP and the subsequent boom of generative AI chatbots. Published on the „The Startup“:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/swlh/a-beginners-guide-to-ai-product-management-eda63ab86db5&#34;&gt;https://medium.com/swlh/a-beginners-guide-to-ai-product-management-eda63ab86db5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to Measure AI Product Performance the Right Way</title>
      <link>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/performance/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sischreiber.com/posts/performance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;AI/machine learning products are data-driven, but paradoxically their impact is not easily quantifiable. My thoughts to this on “The Startup”:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/swlh/how-to-measure-ai-product-performance-the-right-way-2d6791c5f5c3&#34;&gt;https://medium.com/swlh/how-to-measure-ai-product-performance-the-right-way-2d6791c5f5c3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
